[什麼是p值]
If you read articles in
the scientific literature,
你一定常在閱讀科學文獻時
you'll often see people report P-values
when they report statistical tests.
發現統計檢定報告裡有很多p值(p-values)
P-values are widely used, and it's
important to understand what they mean.
p值被廣泛使用，當然要了解其意義
They're also widely criticized, because
people often misinterpret p-values.
p值也倍受批評，因為常有錯誤的推論
So in this lecture, the goal is
to understand what they mean and
這節課程要理解p值所指為何
how to correctly interpret them.
以及正確運用p值推論
When we talk about p-values, the first
question we should ask ourselves is
談到p值，首先要問的問題是
why are they so
popular in scientific articles?
為什麼許多科學文獻都會看到p值？
Well, there's a reason for this, and
Benjamini expresses it quite nicely.
以色列統計學者Yoav Benjamini有很好的回答
He says in some sense it offers
a first line of defense against
他說「起碼來說，p值是避免我們被隨機現象
being fooled by randomness,
separating the signal from the noise.
愚弄的第一道防線，也就是從噪音裡區辨信號」
So, this is what the p-values
allow you to do.
這是p值的基本功能
When you interpret your data,
你對資料進行推論時
you might be very likely to interpret data
in favor of the hypothesis that you have,
應該很期待資料支持你的假設
even when the effect might be only
slightly in the right direction.
即使期待的方向只有一點點效果
The risk is that you're fooling yourself.
冒下結論的後果可能是愚弄自已
You might be too likely to declare
that something is going on,
特別是從只存在隨機變異的資料裡
when you're actually looking
at random variation in data.
宣稱出現有意義的訊息
So, p-values are one way to
prevent you from fooling yourself.
因此p值是避免自已做傻事的一種設計
P-values tell you how surprising the data
is, assuming that there is no effect.
p值是在假設不存在效果的前提下，
告訴你資料之中有沒有驚喜(存在效果)
And we'll look at all these
aspects in more detail.
接下來要解釋這句話的意思
What surprising means,
why they're statements about the data, and
驚喜是指什麼？
為什麼p值能代表資料的狀態？
why they're built on the idea
that there is no effect.
為什麼要先假定不存在任何效果？
Now, some people say
that p-values are more
有些人會說p值是你了解貝式統計前
能正確解釋資料的工具
accurately explained as what you use if
you don't know Bayesian statistics yet.
有些人會說p值是你了解貝式統計前
能正確解釋資料的工具
In Bayesian statistics,
people don't use p-values.
使用貝式統計的人不使用p值推論
And I still remember when I
was doing my own PhD, that I
我還記得當我還在唸博士班時
had this confusion about whether I should
use p-values, or Bayesian statistics.
被到底該用p值還是貝氏統計所困擾
My understanding was, more or less,
that I realized there was some problem
當時的我或多或少以為，有些問題用p值較好
有些用貝氏統計較合適
with using p-values, and Bayesian
statistics might be preferable, but
當時的我或多或少以為，有些問題用p值較好
有些用貝氏統計較合適
most people didn't use
Bayesian statistics.
但是當時很少人使用貝氏統計
So, it was probably fine to
just continue using p-values.
所以那時就跟著一起用p值做統計推論
Now, I think it's fine to use p-values,
but you should interpret them correctly.
現在的我認為只要推論方法正確
p值還是很好用的
So, that's the goal in this lecture,
to prevent this confusion in you,
所以這一講的目標就是掃除你的困擾
and to make sure that you use p-values
correctly, if you decide to use them.
決定使用p值時，能正確使用p值推論
Let's start with a practical example.
用這個實際的例子來說明
Let's say you want to to do a study where
you examine the influence of calling
比方說你要研究開車時講電話的影響
while you are driving.
Does being on the phone when you
are in your car increase the risk of
開車時講電話會增加出車禍的風險嗎？
getting into an accident?
You might design a study where half of
the participants drive around the city
也許你會設計一個研究讓半數參與者在市區開車時
講電話，另一半開車時不講電話
while they're on the phone, and the other
half of the participants drive around, but
也許你會設計一個研究讓半數參與者在市區開車時
講電話，另一半開車時不講電話
they're not on the phone.
也許你會設計一個研究讓半數參與者在市區開車時
講電話，另一半開車時不講電話
You want to see if there's a difference,
你會想看到一些組間差異
maybe in the number of people they hit
while they're driving through the street.
像是一趟下來開車撞人的次數
Or maybe your ethical committee
doesn't allow you to do this,
不過倫理審查委員會大概不允許這麼做
and you're better off using
a driving simulator to study this.
所以最好用駕駛模擬器來做研究
Now, if you have collected your data, you
counted how many people get hit by a car,
假想你已收完資料，要清點每位講電話的駕駛
與沒講電話的駕駛撞到的人數
either by people who are on
the phone while they're driving or
假想你已收完資料，要清點每位講電話的駕駛
與沒講電話的駕駛撞到的人數
people who are not on the phone,
假想你已收完資料，要清點每位講電話的駕駛
與沒講電話的駕駛撞到的人數
then you can look at the difference
between these two conditions.
然後檢查這兩組駕駛之間的表現差異
Now, this difference
is never exactly zero.
兩組的表現差異永遠不會剛好等於零
There's always some number follow after
the comma that makes a difference.
小數點之後總是有除不盡的數字
So, let's say the difference you
observe is 0.11, a mean difference.
假定你收集到的資料，兩組平均差異是0.11
Now, how should you interpret
this mean difference?
你要如何解釋這樣的差異
There are two options.
你有兩種選擇
A, what you are looking at is
probably just random noise.
選擇A，這個數值純粹是隨機變異
There's always some random
noise in your data.
因為研究資料中總是存在隨機變異
Option B, this is probably a real
difference, this is something that
選擇B，可能真的有差異
you should take seriously, and at least
examine further in future studies.
不過要小心，並要在之後的研究再做檢驗
So, which of these two is true.
到底那個選擇才正確？
Well, we can use the p-value to
differentiate between these two options.
我們可以用p值評估兩種選擇的差異
From the data that we have, we can
calculate means, standard deviations, and
我們可以用手上資料計算平均值，標準差
還有樣本數
we know the sample size that we have.
我們可以用手上資料計算平均值，標準差
還有樣本數
We can use these parameters to
calculate a test statistic, and
我們可以使用這些參數(parameters)計算統計值
compare this test statistic
against a distribution.
統計值能拿來與機率分配(distribution)做比較
You can use many different
types of distributions.
能用的機率分配(distribution)相當多種
If you examine precognition, you might
want to use a paranormal distribution.
像是要檢驗預知能力，也許需要超常分配
(請介紹給前台大校長李教授)
But most often,
people just use the normal distribution.
不過大部分情況，我們只需要常態分配
So, this bell shaped graph is
something you might have seen before.
你可能曾在其它地方看過這樣的鐘型曲線
And there's something you
should note here, and
要特別注意的地方是
that's that this distribution
is centered on zero.
常態分配的中心位於0
And when we talk about the p-value
being data that is surprising,
我們說如果p值顯示資料之中有驚奇
assuming the null is true, the null
hypothesis is true, this is what we mean.
是建立虛無假設為真的前提，就是指中心位於0
的常態分配
We look at a distribution
centered at zero.
是建立虛無假設為真的前提，就是指中心位於0
的常態分配
Now, you can see that most of
the data in this case, let's look
如果虛無假設的確為真，就有95%的資料
屬於圖中的著色區域
at 95% of the data,
will fall between two critical values.
也就是剛好落於兩個臨界值之間
And these critical values, you might
have seen this number, 1.96 and -1.96.
圖中可以看到這兩個臨界值1.96 與 -1.96
These are critical values if you
want to use an alpha level of 0.05.
若你設定顯著水準為0.05，會得到這兩個臨界值
If data falls between these two values,
it's not surprising.
如果由資料算出來的統計值落在兩個臨界值之間
就沒有驚奇
Assuming that the null hypothesis is true,
再講一次，假設虛無假設確實為值
most of the data will fall between
these two critical values.
多數資料算出來的統計值落在兩個臨界值之間
But sometimes, we might see a data
point that's more extreme than this.
不過有時資料會落到臨界值之外
And this is a surprising find.
這就是出現驚喜的情況
This is surprising data whenever the mean
difference, or the test statistic that is
從平均值差異計算的統計值，只要落在任何一邊
的臨界值之外，就代表資料之中有驚喜
computed from this mean difference, is in
one of the two tails of this distribution.
從平均值差異計算的統計值，只要落在任何一側
的臨界值之外，就代表資料之中有驚喜
So, whenever we find that data that
falls in these tails, it's surprising.
只要我們發現資料出現在任一側
就代表出現驚喜
And we might want to examine it further.
再進一步檢查的話，會發現對應的p值小於0.05
It also means that the p-value's
smaller than 0.05.
再進一步檢查的話，會發現對應的p值小於0.05
The formal definition of a p-value is
the probability of getting the observed,
p值的正式定義是，在虛無假設為真的前提下
觀察值或「極端資料」屬於此分配的機率
or more extreme data,
assuming the null hypothesis is true.
p值的正式定義是，在虛無假設為真的前提下
觀察值或「極端資料」屬於此分配的機率
Now, I highlighted the word data here.
我特別把「資料」標示出來
I think it's important to realize that
we're talking about the probability of
是提醒大家，p值代表觀察到這項資料的「機率」
observing data.
A p-value is the probability
that you'll observe some data,
p值是你會觀察到這項資料的機率
P(Data|Theory)
but not the probability of a theory.
不是你的理論為真的機率
P(Theory)
This is a very common misunderstanding.
後一句話是常見的誤解
People often want to make a statement
about the probability that
許多人想用理論為真的機率支持自已的主張
the theory is true.
But when you calculate a p-value,
但是你算出p值後，能主張的只是
獲得這項資料的機率
all you can do is make a statement
about the probability of the data.
但是你算出p值後，能主張的只是
獲得這項資料的機率
Now, if you make this mistake,
you're in good company.
如果現在的你也有同樣的誤解
那你並不孤單
Let's take a look at this example from
quantum physics, where a physicist talks
來看看量子力學的實際例子，物理學家想知道
觀察到不同地點的粒子同時自旋機率
about the probability of observing
a certain spin between quantum particles.
來看看量子力學的實際例子，物理學家想知道
觀察到不同地點的粒子同時自旋機率
So, this is a study where they
measured the spin in a particle levels
發表這篇論文的物理學家，有些人在台夫特(Delft)
floating around somewhere in Delft,
and another one that was floating
測量粒子自旋，同時另一批人在阿姆斯特丹
around somewhere in Amsterdam,
in the Netherlands, and
對另一顆粒子進行相同的測量
these two particles spin together,
they have some sort of relationship.
他們想從測量的結果，推論兩顆同時自旋的粒子
And this relationship, based on the data,
彼此之間存在什麼關係
was statistically significant
with a p-value of 0.04.
因為他們得到p值為0.04的統計顯著結果
Now, some physicist is interviewed
about this finding, and this physicist
其中某位物理學家接受訪問談他們的發現
concludes, in other words, there is
a 96% probability they won the race.
這位學者以統計結果宣稱有96%的機率，
他們的理論正確預測這兩顆粒子的關係
So, this person is making a mistake
here because, with won the race,
這樣的宣稱其實是錯誤的
this person means there's a 96%
probability that this theory is correct.
96%的機率在理論上是正確的
But this is a statement about a theory.
但是這只是基於理論做出的結論
It's not a statement about
the data that you have observed.
並不是基於觀察到的資料做出結論
So it's comforting, maybe,
that a quantum physicist,
聽完這例子你應該感到很欣慰
which sounds like you're
supposed to be really smart,
量子物理學家應該比一般人聰明
also makes this misinterpretation
of what a p-value means.
也會搞錯p值的真正意義
After you have observed a p-value
that's smaller than 0.05,
如果說你分析今天收完的資料確實發現
小於0.05的p值
for example,
an effect is not 95% likely to be true.
也不能說你發現的效果有95%的機率是真的
Think about pre-cognition research.
拿超感知覺(pre-cognition)的案例來說
(Bem, 2011. JPSP)
Let's say that I present
one study to you where you
你讀到其中一項實驗報告
find a statistically significant
effect of pre-cognition.
超常知覺的實驗效果有統計顯著
After this, do you really think it's now
95% probable that pre-cognition exists?
你能相信有95%的機率超感知覺確實存在？
Probably not,
you cannot get the probability
你應該不相信
你不可能把p值當成根據現在結果
that the null hypothesis is true,
given the data from a p-value.
支持(虛無)假設為真的真實機率
If you look at the two statements below on
the screen, you see that the probability
仔細看這張投影片最下面的不等式
of the data, or more extreme data,
assuming the null hypothesis is true.
左邊是(虛無)假設為真，
獲得超出臨界值資料的條件機率
It's not the same as
the probability of an hypothesis
右邊是現在獲得的資料，
能證實假設為真的條件機率
given some data that you have observed.
右邊是現在獲得的資料，
能證實假設為真的條件機率
This two probabilities can differ widely.
兩個條件機率不能彼此互換
If you want to know the probability
that the theory is true,
想知道理論為真的機率，必須使用貝式統計
you need to use Bayesian statistics.
Bayesian statistics is the only
approach that will allow you to make
貝式統計是唯一能計算理論為真之機率的方法
statements about the probability
that the theory is true.
貝式統計是唯一能計算理論為真之機率的方法
What happens if you do a study and
your p-value is larger than 0.05?
當你的研究得到大於0.05的p值該怎麼辦？
Well first of course, you spend a lot of
time and effort collecting this data, and
也許你首先想到自已花了這麼久時間收集資料
maybe you hope to find
the statistically significant effect.
滿心期待能獲得顯著的統計效果
So the first thing you do is cry a little,
you're a little bit depressed.
看到不顯著的結果會想先躲起來哭哭
That's okay, But after this how
should you interpret this data?
療愈完畢還要面對如何用這份資料做推論？
Well, all that we know when
the p-value is larger than
再次提醒大於0.05的p值
代表的只是這次觀察的結果沒有驚喜
0.05 is that the data we have observed
is not surprising, that's all.
再次提醒大於0.05的p值
代表的只是這次觀察的結果沒有驚喜
It doesn't mean that
there is no true effect.
不顯著不是不存在真實效果
There might very well be in effect but
只是剛好參與你的研究的參與者人數不多
所以無法偵測到這個效果
you just didn't have enough participants
in your study to detect this effect.
只是剛好參與你的研究的參與者人數不多
所以無法偵測到這個效果
Remember that you need large samples
to statistically detect a small effect.
隨時記得小效果需要大樣本才能達到統計顯著
So just because your
p-value is larger than 0.05
不要因為p值大於0.05就妄下沒有效果的結論
(中研院前院長翁啟惠很了解這點)
doesn't allow you to conclude
that there is no effect.
不要因為p值大於0.05就妄下沒有效果的結論
(中研院前院長翁啟惠很了解這點)
There might be very small effect,
you don't know.
你並不清楚有沒有存在相當微小的效果
Personally, I try to think of
a p-value larger than 0.05 as mu,
我個人喜歡把大於0.05的p值當成「無」
(外國人發音類似mu，希臘字母μ)
which is a concept from Zen Buddhism.
這是源自禪宗的概念
In Zen Buddhism, there is a famous
saying that goes like this.
中國唐代趙州從諗禪師留下這一則公案
(狗子佛性)
A monk asked a Chinese Zen master,
does a dog have a Buddha-nature or not?
有僧人問禪師「狗子有佛性乎？」
So you might expect a yes or
由你來答的話，也許會想這是個是非題
不是有就是沒有
no answer here because that's also how
the question is phrased yes or no.
由你來答的話，也許會想這是個是非題
不是有就是沒有
But instead the Zen master answered mu,
which basically means I'm on
不過禪師會根據問者的角度回答
asking the question it's negating
the question that's asked.
這則公案點出這種問題沒有是非對錯
Whenever you find a p-value
that's larger than 0.05,
回頭看你發現自已的結果p值大於0.05
you might feel the tendency to say so
is there an effect or not?
你本來有一股勁要說「真的存在這個效果」
But whenever the p-value is larger than
0.05, you can't answer this question.
大於0.05的p值卻讓你說不出口
So you should just answer mu.
所以最好的答案應該是「無(這種問題)」
So how do you use p-values correctly?
那麼要如何正確使用p值推論？
The first thing to understand
is that p-values can be use
要先了解p值是提供研究者
長期行動準則
as a rule to guide
behavior in the long run.
要先了解p值是提供研究者
長期行動準則
You can calculate them for every single
study, but they only work in the long run.
每次研究都可以得到一個p值
但是要長期累積才能顯出意義
Let's take a look how.
我們來看怎麼回事
If you use the decision rule whenever the
p-value is smaller than the alpha level,
只要你採取判斷p值是否小於顯著水準的規則
so this is your type one error rate,
which is often set to 0.05,
就會得到型一錯誤率，通常我們設定為0.05
you can act as if the data is not noise.
這條規則說
「如果資料並非雜訊，你就能採取行動」
Now this word act is very important.
「採取行動」的真正意義很重要
It's independent of what you believe is
true, but all that you know is, if you use
這無關你相信什麼是真的，當你使用這規則
推論數萬筆沒有訊息的資料，除了其中5%
this decision rule in the long run,
you won't say that there is something,
這無關你相信什麼是真的，當你使用這規則
推論數萬筆沒有訊息的資料，除了其中5%
when there is nothing,
more than 5% of the time.
你都會宣稱沒有任何訊息
Alternatively, when the p-value is larger
than the alpha you can remain uncertain or
另一條規則說「得到大於顯著水準的p值，
act as if the data is just noise.
你可以保持不確定或視資料是一堆雜訊」
So these are rules that you
follow in the long run.
以上就是你的長期行動準則
When you act as if there is an effect
whenever the p-value is smaller than 0.05,
以小於0.05的p值宣稱存在一種效果，
你做上萬次資料分析出錯機率不會超過5%
in the long run you won't be
wrong more than 5% of the time.
以小於0.05的p值宣稱存在一種效果，
你做上萬次資料分析出錯機率不會超過5%
Now this is an interpretation of p-values
as proposed by name and it's often used.
p值的推論模式正如其名，
而且用途很廣泛
Let's take the discovery of
the Higgs boson as an example.
來看看宣稱發現希格斯玻色子的報告
If you're a remember, during the press
conference about the Higgs boson,
請找一下宣佈這項發現的新聞
(CERN, 2012/06/22)
researchers were talking about whether
the 5 sigma threshold was passed.
研究人員提到實驗結果超過5個標準差
And 5 sigma is used as a threshold to
declare something a discovery in physics.
物理學裡定義5個標準差
是確定事實存在的標準
Now 5 sigma is basically
a p-value smaller than 0.0000003.
換算成p值是小於0.0000003
So based on this idea,
we can act as if the Higgs boson is true.
根據規則，我們可以當希格斯玻色子存在
而採取行動(CERN發佈新聞)
Every now and
即使是如此高的標準，說不定那一天
我們會發現這個結論是錯誤的
then of course we'll be wrong with
such a high threshold for an error.
即使是如此高的標準，說不定那一天
我們會發現這個結論是錯誤的
We'll only be wrong in one of many
billions of parallel universes.
如果有上萬個平行宇宙
只有其中一個會確認這發現是錯的
So there's one parallel universe
where people spend the time and
想像在上萬個平行宇宙裡
effort to build a large Hadron Collider
to detect the Higgs boson and
都有建造偵測希格斯玻色子的大型強子對撞機
they declared it was
a statistically significance.
而且都發現統計顯著的結果
So it was they were actually wrong but
根據如此高的標準，所有平行宇宙發現都是錯
的機率是相當微小
with such a high threshold this
of course rarely happens and
根據如此高的標準，所有平行宇宙發現都是錯
的機率是相當微小
we can be pretty safe that there is a
Higgs boson and we didn't make a mistake.
所以我們可以確信希格斯玻色子真的存在
而且相信不會發現任何反證
When you interpret p-values and
you want to write something about what you
在報告中如此寫下對p值的推論是錯的：
「因為p值小於.05，我們的理論獲得證實」
found you should not write, we found a
p-value smaller than 0.05, so our theory.
在報告中如此寫下對p值的推論是錯的：
「因為p值小於.05，我們的理論獲得證實」
Because if you do this, you're
making a statement about this theory
這麼做是依據p值做出對理論的陳述
稍早(8分24秒)已說明這是錯的
based on a p-value and
you shouldn't do this.
這麼做是依據p值做出對理論的陳述
稍早(8分24秒)已說明這是錯的
The correct way to discuss a p-value
smaller than 0.05 is to say we
正確的報告應該這樣寫：
「因為p值小於.05，我們的資料符合預期」
found the p-value smaller than 0.05,
so our data.
正確的報告應該這樣寫：
「因為p值小於.05，我們的資料符合預期」
You make a statement about the data
because that's what the p-value
這樣的報告是根據p值陳述資料的狀況
relates to.
You might say something like, so
接著才能加些說明
our data is in line with some
idea that you want to test.
像是資料與要測試的理論預測一致
Whenever you found a known significant
result, a p-value larger than 0.05.
要是你做的研究p值大於0.05，是曾經有人
發現顯著統計結果的研究
You enter what's known as
a degenerative research line.
那你就是遇上了「退化性研究進程」
(degenerative research line:參考Imre Laktos)
You made a prediction but
it doesn't hold up.
事前有預測卻沒有符合的發現
So you have something to explain.
必須要花更多功夫解釋
Now one explanation might
just be random variation.
其中一種解釋是隨機變異
P-values vary and even if you have
examined a true effect, every now and
即使你檢視的是真實效果，p值變異有可能
導致你某次的研究出現不顯著的結果
then you'll observe
a non-significant result.
即使你檢視的是真實效果，p值變異有可能
導致你某次的研究出現不顯著的結果
So you might just say,
everything's fine, this happens.
第一次你也許會想「沒關係，剛好而己」
If I do another study that's exactly the
same, you'll see that it will pan out and
若是再作一次還是不顯著，你也許會想
「總會做出來的，理論應該沒問題」
my prediction will hold.
若是再作一次還是不顯著，你也許會想
「總會做出來的，理論應該沒問題」
Other times, you might need to say,
但是第三次還是不顯著，也許會開始想
well the effect that I predicted
might be smaller than I expected.
「實際的效果可能比我預期效果還小」
So you do another study,
but it's larger and
抱著這樣心態做最後一次，
搞不好發現了更大的效果
then you show that
the effect is really there.
這時總算可以宣佈確實有效果
Nevertheless, whenever you
find a non-significant result,
無論如何，一旦遇上了不顯著結果
there is something to think about.
必有一些事情要好好考慮
You have to explain it in some way.
你必須採取某種解釋方法
One way might be, if you do a lot of
studies, every now and then you will find
一種方法是持續累積大量不顯著的結果
但是需要進行相當多次才能支持你的看法
a non significant result, but then you
need a lot of studies to support this.
一種方法是持續累積大量不顯著的結果
但是需要進行相當多次才能支持你的看法
Other times you might say, I have to do
the study in a slightly different way, and
還有一種方法是改變一下研究設計
you can use this change in the paradigm
to develop a progressive research line.
因此而讓研究方法更容易偵測效果，就會促成
「進步性研究進程」(progressive research line)
Remember that p-values vary so
要做到如此，必須記得
要以整合分析的角度思考每個p值的意義
always think meta-analytically
about p-values.
要做到如此，必須記得
要以整合分析的角度思考每個p值的意義
This is also recommended by the
statisticians who talked about p-values in
開發p值運用方法的元祖統計學家也這樣建議
the very beginning.
For example,
this is a quote by Neyman and Pearson.
就像這摘自尼曼與皮爾森(1928)論文的一段話
Statistical tests should
be used with discretion and
「統計檢定必須在有洞見與認識的狀況下使用，
而非被當作試誤的工具」
understanding, and not as instruments
which themselves give the final verdict.
「統計檢定必須在有洞見與認識的狀況下使用，
而非被當作試誤的工具」
So if you fail a statistical
test that's only one thing
如果資料無法通過計檢定
that should go into your reasoning to
decide whether this is a true effect.
要做的是反省判斷真實效果的推理過程
Always think more about your study.
永遠要先考慮自已的研究條件
P-value might be a starting points, but
you also want to look at effect sizes and
p值不過是分析的開始，也要檢視效果量
other studies that have been done.
還要參考曾在相同條件做過的研究
Fisher similarly says
that a single p-value was
費雪(1937)也有類似的看法
not enough to declare some discovery on.
主張一個p值不足以宣稱「真正發現某物」
He says, a phenomenon is experimentally
demonstrable when we know how
他說「能透過實驗呈現的現象，
是因為這項實驗極少出現
to conduct an experiment which
will rarely fail to give
他說「能透過實驗呈現的現象，
是因為這項實驗極少出現
us a statistically significant result.
不顯著的統計結果」
So we have to repeat
the experiment multiple times.
這也是為什麼必須多次重覆相同實驗
He also says, no isolated experiment,
however significant in itself,
費雪還說「就算單一實驗結果是顯著的，
也不能代表這項結果呈現任何自然現象」
can suffice for the experimental
demonstration of any natural phenomenon.
費雪還說「就算單一實驗結果是顯著的，
也不能代表這項結果呈現任何自然現象」
So he's saying that we
should see a single p-value,
他主張單一p值是提示有更多值得
探索的事實
maybe as an invitation to
explore this effect further, but
他主張單一p值是提示有更多值得
探索的事實
it can never be enough to declare
something a scientific fact.
並不能用來宣稱發現某項科學事實
So we always need to
do several studies and
我們必須儘可能多做重覆研究
p-values can guide us in the long run
in which studies we might want to do.
運用p值在過程中改進研究條件
So, at the end of this lecture,
終於來到這一講的尾聲
let's take a look at the p-values that you
can expect when there is a true effect.
假想要從這一堆p值找出預期的真實效果
And the p-values that you might
expect when there is no true effect.
以及從另一堆p值確定不存在真實效果
Now, I never really realized how
p-values are distributed across studies
只是沒人知道這些來自不同研究的p值
形成什麼的分配？
when you do a lot of them.
只是沒人知道這些來自不同研究的p值
形成什麼的分配？
And I think it's very important
to understand this for
如何正確推論p值的意義是這一講的重點
the correct interpretation of a p-value.
So take a moment to think about this.
現在請你花點時間想想
What kind of p-values would you
expect when there is a true effect?
你會期待從什麼樣的p值發現真實效果？
What kind of p-values would you
expect when there is no effect?
還有從什麼樣的p值發現不存在真實效果？
Let's take a look what really happens.
現在來看看正確答案
When there is a true effect,
存在真實效果時，p值的分配形態
決定於統計考驗力
the p-value distribution depends
on the statistical power.
存在真實效果時，p值的分配形態
決定於統計考驗力
Let's take a look at
the visualization of this.
來看看模擬結果的視覺化
In this graph, you see the p-values for
100,000 studies,
這張圖是100,000項研究的p值次數分配
where every study had
50% statistical power.
而且每項研究統計考驗力都是50%
This means that it's 50% probable
that we'll observe a p-value
也就是說做一次這項研究有50%的機率
獲得小於0.05的p值
that's smaller than 0.05.
也就是說做一次這項研究有50%的機率
獲得小於0.05的p值
If we look at the p-value distribution,
we indeed see that it's much more likely
仔細看這張圖會發現
獲得微小p值的可能性比大p值高很多
to observe small p-values,
than it is to observe high p-values.
仔細看這張圖會發現
獲得微小p值的可能性比大p值高很多
And if we look at the leftmost bar,
we see that indeed 50,000 of the 100,000
特別是最左邊的這一條
是其中50,000項研究p值累積而成
simulated studies yield a p-value
that falls between 0 and 0.05.
這些p值都落在0與0.05之間
Now, we might want to increase
the statistical power a little bit.
接著把統計考驗力提高一些(80%)
You see that with higher power
we have basically pushed more of
會看到小於0.05的p值會增加
推高分配左側的高度
the p-values below the significance
threshold of 0.05.
會看到小於0.05的p值會增加
推高分配左側的高度
Here we have 80,000 of the 100,000
有顯著結果的模擬研究次數來到80,000次
simulated studies that
yield a significant effect.
有顯著結果的模擬研究次數來到80,000次
If we increase the statistical
power even more, to 95%,
若是再把統計考驗力增加到95%
we now see that most of
the p-values that we'll observe,
因為確實存在真實效果
given that there is a true effect,
will fall below the significance level.
幾乎所有研究的p值都在顯著水準之下
So which p-values can you
expect when there is no effect?
那麼如果沒有真實效果的p值分配是什麼樣子？
I really never knew this myself.
以前我從未仔細想過
I thought that p-values might
be distributed in a way that,
我以為這種情況大於顯著水準的p值
會比較多，次數分配右側會比較高
if there's no effect,
we'll see a lot of very high p-values.
我以為這種情況大於顯著水準的p值
會比較多，次數分配右側會比較高
Or I thought that it's possible
that maybe they're distributed
或者是變成中間較高的常態分配
as sort of a normal distribution,
but instead it turns out,
或者是變成中間較高的常態分配
that when there is no effect,
p-values are uniformly distributed.
結果出乎我的意料，
實際是形成均勻分配
Every p-value is equally likely.
也就是獲得任何p值的可能性是相同的
And it also makes a lot of
sense if you understand it.
數據模擬也能讓我們了解這是怎麼回事
In this case, we have simulated 100,000
studies where there is no true effect.
這是100,000項沒有真實效果的研究模擬結果
And you see that, no matter where
you look in the distribution,
如圖所示橫軸上的任何一個p值
low p-values or high p-values,
they're all equally likely.
從高到低出現的可能性都是相等的
Now this makes sense because in this way,
這樣的結果是很合理的
when there is a uniform distribution
it means that 5% of the p-values that
沒有真實效果的研究考驗力接近顯著水準
we observe when there is no effect,
fall below the 0.05 threshold.
造成僅有其中5%的p值出現在顯著水準之下
So when there's no effect, we have a 5%
probability of making a type one error of
沒有真實效果的研究會有5%的型一錯誤率
saying there is a significant effect
when there's actually nothing going on.
也就是沒有效果卻出現顯著結果的情況
So here you can see this small type
one error rate highlighted in red.
把最左邊的這一條挑出來仔細看
So this is what it means
to make a type one error.
高度恰好等於型一錯誤率
The reason that it's 5% is because
there's a uniform p-value distribution.
為何顯著水準約定俗成0.05，
正是因為這樣的均勻分配
If you would increase your
alpha level to 0.10 there's
就算把顯著水準提高到0.10
still 10% of the p-values
that fall below 0.10.
數據模擬告訴我們只有10%的p值落於0.10之下
To conclude, it's important to understand
how to correctly interpret the p-value.
總歸一句，正確推論p值的意義是很重要的
Its use is often criticized because people
incorrectly interpret what p-values mean.
p值的用途常被人詬病
是因為多數人錯誤推論p值的意義
And I hope that after this lecture,
you won't be one of them.
希望上完這一講的你不再犯和多數人一樣的錯誤
[課程結束]